A Guide to the John D. Rockefeller, Sr. papers FA002
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence, 1804-1896; C; 34.4 Cubic Feet 86 boxes
  - Office, O; 20 Cubic Feet 50 boxes
    - McDonald - McKay, 149 Pages (Box 25, Folder 197, Reel 22, Frame 0736)
      Standard Oil Company executives; trotting horses; personal aid; Mariners' Family Asylum; Mount Hermon School (Dwight L. Moody's school); Baptist Church; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church Sunday school; Standard Oil Trust shares; personal loans; Pan-Republic Congress and Human Freedom League; University of Michigan; Catholic Church; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); Woman's Baptist Foreign Missionary Society; Fifth Avenue Baptist church organist; real estate; road improvements; Gospel Training College; house painter; temperance work; Hampden-Sidney College; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU).
    - McKean - McLaurin, 54 Pages (Reel 22, Frame 0885, Box 26, Folder 198)
      Deaconess movement; Baptist Church; personal aid; oil business; Central Refining Company; Standard Oil Company; New York Gospel Tent; Grande Ligne Mission, Canada; trotting horses; real estate mortgage; Sunday school; personal aid.
    - McLean, Alexander, 1879-1894; 108 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0001, Box 26, Folder 199)
      Stableman at Forest Hill; care and transportation of horses; payment of bills and salaries.
    - McLeish - MacRady, 38 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0109, Box 26, Folder 200)
      University of Chicago; Rockford Seminary; ranch in Texas; attorney; Andrews, Clark & Company; oil lands in Pennsylvania; Driving Club of New York; John D. Rockefeller servant; treatment of reformed drunkard at Ward's Island mental hospital; article on oil fields; proposed Baptist College or Academy.
    - MacRae, Charles, 1880-1891; 98 Pages (Box 26, Folder 201, Reel 23, Frame 0147)
      Real estate agent; 4 West 54th Street; negotiations; H. M. Flagler.
    - MacRae, Charles, 1892-1893; 85 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0245, Box 26, Folder 202)
    - McSwyney - Manly, 143 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0330, Box 26, Folder 203)
      First Anniversary of the Centennial Celebration of Washington's Inauguration; proposed college of the Missionary Baptist Church of North Missouri; Baptist Church Sunday school; American Baptist Missionary Union; new ticker tape for New York Stock Exchange; Gold & Stock Telegraph Company; real estate; masseur; personal aid; job applicant; Equitable Life Assurance Society; Union Academy (Negro), Gainesville, Florida; Baptist Church; Standard Oil Trust shares; Reformed Dutch Church; Clinton College; Morningside Park speeding driveway; Loyal Legion Temperance Society; personal loan; International Medical Missionary Society; Harlem Medical Mission; F. T. Gates report; Benedict Institute (Negro), South Carolina; Manhattan Eye & Ear Hospital; Southern Baptist Theological Seminary.
    - Mann - Marston, C. C., 70 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0473, Box 26, Folder 204)
      General Missionary to Deaf-Mutes; Fifth Avenue Baptist Church; American Baptist Missionary Union; "Manufacturers' Record;" Baptist Church; Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA); attorney; real estate; Day Nursery; jewelers; aid for printing sermon; coal and wood dealer; "The Art Amateur;" lightning protection; American Fine Arts Society; Washington Memorial Arch Fund; Metropolitan Museum of Art; John D. Rockefeller office employees; School for Christian Workers; character reference; American Sunday School Mission; State Charities Aid Association of New York; personal aid; personal loan; paintings for sale; Baptist Young People's Union of Western Washington and British Columbia.
    - Marston, E. L., 1892-1894; 71 Pages (Box 26, Folder 205, Reel 23, Frame 0543)
      Fifth Avenue Baptist Church assistant treasurer; John D. Rockefeller contributions; work of the church; Baptist Church appeals; F. T. Gates report; New York Baptist City Mission; American Baptist Missionary Union; American Baptist Publication Society; Armitage House Day Nursery and Kindergarten; American Baptist Home Mission Society; Blair & Company; stock market activity; Providence & Springfield Railroad Company.
    - Mart - Material Men's Mercantile Association, 76 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0614, Box 26, Folder 206)
      Fifth Avenue Baptist Church organist; Baptist Church; job applicants; oil business; disaster relief (cyclone); Colored Baptist Church; University of Chicago lawsuit; real estate; Continental Oil Company; personal matters; Bank of New York; India missionary; furniture manufacturer; Methodist Episcopal Church; Baptist Female School; National Mary Washington Memorial Association; books for sale; personal loan; Material Men's Mercantile Association.
    - Mather, A. E. - Mather, Flora S., 83 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0690, Box 26, Folder 207)
      Baptist Ministers' Home, Fenton, Michigan; Baptist Ministers' Aid Society; John D. Rockefeller contributions; F. T. Gates report; Woman's Christian Association; Day Nursery and Free Kindergarten Association; Standard Oil Company employees.
    - Mathew - Meredith, 155 Pages (Reel 23, Frame 0773, Box 27, Folder 208)
      Personal loan; personal aid; Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York; paint dealer; Christian Brothers' College; paintings for sale; curios dealer; Baptist Church; violin teacher; theological questions; Baylor Female College; job applicant; Presbyterian Church; Poland Union Seminary; Standard Oil Company stationery department; office supplies; College Preparatory School for Women; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); German Baptist Church; Lutheran Church; Law and Order Association; temperance work; Edwards' Parlor Lamp Stove Company; Cherry Street Kindergarten; Sioux Falls University; American Baptist Home Mission Society.
    - Meriam - Mey, 112 Pages (Box 27, Folder 209, Reel 23, Frame 0928)
      Job applicant; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); burglar alarm; personal loan; Baptist Church; corn futures investment; Women and Children's Free Dispensary; Huron Street Hospital; Cleveland Homeopathic Hospital; Western New York Society for Homeless and Dependent Children; coal mines in Illinois; Rochester Theological Seminary; paintings for sale; sporting goods; photographic demonstration; Methodist Episcopal Church; Congregational Church; Metropolitan Club; electrical contractor; American Art Association.
    - Meyer - Mills, H. E., 151 Pages (Box 27, Folder 210, Reel 24, Frame 0001)
      Barnard college; Baptist Church; Doan Hall Gospel Temperance Union; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); attorney; personal aid; music concert; Turkey missionary; shirt makers; Arkansas Baptist College (Negro work); landscape gardener; Methodist Episcopal Church; Barcelona Protestant Cottage-Hospital in Spain; private school for boys and girls; Israel missionary; John D. Rockefeller office employee; Galena Oil Works; coal, iron, and timber lands in Kentucky; silk quilt; Louisiana Female College; Wagner Palace Car Company; John D. Rockefeller lost umbrella; St. Luke's Hospital; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); New York School of Languages; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. education; Orpheus Glee Club of New York; John D. Rockefeller relative; personal loan; General Theological Library; Pocantico Hills employee; Union League Club; Association for the Preservation of Fifth Avenue as a Thoroughfare; Shurtleff College.
    - Mills, J. P. - Mizer, 155 Pages (Box 27, Folder 211, Reel 24, Frame 0152)
      American Sabbath Union; Baptist Minister's Home; Baptist Ministers' Home Society; F. T. Gates report; personal aid; New York Christian Home for Intemperate Men; John D. Rockefeller servant (John McPheleny); treatment of reformed drunkard at Ward's Island mental hospital; personal loan; lecturer; timberlands in Virginia; student assistance; New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor; Committee of Fifty; Waco Female College; oil refining proposals; Anti-Saloon Republican League; Vassar College; Baptist Academy; real estate.
    - Moale - Mooney, 131 Pages (Box 27, Folder 212, Reel 24, Frame 0307)
      Baltimore United Oil Company trustees; Standard Oil Company subsidiaries; personal aid; Baptist Church; personal loan; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church; Baptist College; timberlands in Alabama and Florida; Union League Club; Southern historical Society; Virginia Historical Society; John D. Rockefeller school mate; job applicant; Carson and Newman College; Cuba missionary; Mount Hermon Boys' School (Dwight L. Moody's School); Northfield Seminary for Young Ladies; American Sunday School Union; Bible Institute for Home and Foreign Missions; Chicago Evangelization Society.
    - Moore, Cornelia S., 1886-1894; 92 Pages (Reel 24, Frame 0438, Box 27, Folder 213)
      Housekeeper at Forest Hill; remodeling of house; invested money with John D. Rockefeller; Natural Gas Trust shares; Standard Oil Trust shares; personal aid for family.
    - Moore, E. C. - Morehouse, C. S., 39 Pages (Reel 24, Frame 0530, Box 27, Folder 214)
      Masseur; University of Rochester; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) International Committee; interview request; Baptist Church; American Baptist Home Mission Society; yacht for rent; patent for tin-plating; bottle-stopper invention; personal loan.
    - Morehouse, Henry L., 1881-1886; 161 Pages (Reel 24, Frame 0569, Box 28, Folder 215)
      American Baptist Home Mission Society, secretary; John D. Rockefeller contributions through society; Church Edifice Fund; Indian University (later Bacone University); Kentucky Normal and Theological Institute; Richmond Institute; Spelman Seminary; Shaw University; Mexico City Mission; Chinese Mission; University of Chicago; University of Rochester; F. T. Gates report; contributions to Colored educational work.
    - Morehouse, Henry L., 1887-1889; 139 Pages (Reel 24, Frame 0730, Box 28, Folder 216)
    - Morehouse, Henry L., 1890-18984; 103 Pages (Box 28, Folder 217, Reel 24, Frame 0869)
    - Morgan - Morse, G. R., 113 Pages (Box 28, Folder 218, Reel 25, Frame 0001)
      Business loan; Baptist Church; Armenia missionary; personal aid; job applicant; brewer; Murphy meetings; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); Presidential Retiring Fund; Euclid Light Infantry; Anarchist meeting; German Baker's Union; Machinists' Union; Poor Fund; New England Society; art teacher; Spelman Seminary; American Baptist Home Mission Society; Church Edifice Fund; Merrian & Morgan Paraffin Company; Castle Garden Concerts; Baptist Church; Congregational Church; Methodist Episcopal Church; personal loan; Methodist Church in England; National Deaf-Mute College; Pottstown Iron company; real estate taxes in Iowa; Oberlin college; Christopher Columbus Monument; Peddie Institute; Vassar College; student assistance.
    - Morse, Oliver C., 1882-1893; 61 Pages (Box 28, Folder 219, Reel 25, Frame 0114)
      Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); John D. Rockefeller contributions; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) Training School; School for Christian Workers; physical education.
    - Morse, Richard C., 1884-1894; 150 Pages (Reel 25, Frame 0175, Box 28, Folder 220)
      Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) International Committee; John D. Rockefeller contributions; College YMCA; Japan YMCA; YMCA Railroad Department.
    - Morse, S. B. - Mosier, 79 Pages (Reel 25, Frame 0325, Box 28, Folder 221)
      California College; Baptist Church; McCune College; Cuba missionary; Southern Baptist Convention; Teachers' Mutual Benefit Association; Baptist Church mission work; fresh air work; personal aid.
    - Moss - Murray, George (Mrs.), 127 Pages (Reel 25, Frame 0404, Box 29, Folder 222)
      Anti-Saloon Republican League; Toronto Baptist Theological Seminary; Baptist Church; Masonic Widows and Orphans Home; Oberlin College; student assistance; personal aid; threat of socialism; tailor; death card; Cleveland Hospital for Women and Children; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) mission school; St. Luke's Hospital; Gogebic Range charity; Female Seminary; University of the City of New York; music teacher; Cleveland Stone Company; American Baptist Missionary Union; missionary work in Burma, Germany, India, Russia, and Sweden; Murphy meetings; temperance work.
    - Murray, George W. - Myler, 103 Pages (Reel 25, Frame 0531, Box 29, Folder 223)
      Berean Baptist Church; Judson Memorial Church; attorney; real estate; church construction plans; Ireland missionaries; Virginia Military Institute; Albert Lea College, School for Young Women; McCune College; personal aid; business proposals; Masonic Order; Equitable Life Assurance Society; tontine insurance plan; Baptist Church.
    - Nagle - Newlon, 157 Pages (Reel 25, Frame 0634, Box 29, Folder 224)
      Wisconsin State Prison; prisoner assistance; Baptist Church; Female Seminary in Texas; European travel plans; Standard Oil Company employee; National Academy of Design; National League for the Protection of American Institutions; National Temperance Society and Publication House; Natural Science Association of America; book on birds; Baptist Female College; Adelbert College; "Iconographic Encyclopedia of the Arts and Sciences;" Association Hospital; Swedish Lutheran Church; business loan; furniture; Brooklyn Maternity Hospital; real estate; mines in Arizona; Society for the Prevention of Crime; transportation of horses; John D. Rockefeller travel arrangements; revocation of railroad passes; Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railway Company; job applicants; personal loan.
    - Newman - New York Steam Company, 63 Pages (Box 29, Folder 225, Reel 25, Frame 0791)
      Baptist Church; personal aid; excursion boat pass; job applicant; student assistance; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); New England Conservatory of Music; New England Society; New York Ballot Reform League; New York Chorus Society; New York Free Circulating Library; New York Driving Club; New York Electric Equipment Company; New York Horse Manure Company; New York Juvenile Guardian Society, Fresh Air Fund; New York Medical College and Hospital for Women (Homeopathic); F. T. Gates report; New York Steam company; New York Central and Hudson River Railroad Company; John D. Rockefeller Western trip; New York "World;" Toronto Baptist College.
    - Nibloe - Northrop, 132 Pages (Box 29, Folder 226, Reel 25, Frame 0854)
      John D. Rockefeller relative; personal aid; student assistance; City Improvement Society; Baptist Church; oil and gas business; competition; paintings for sale; Germany missionary (Alsace-Lorraine, present-day France); Reformed Church of America; Palestine Orphan Asylum; Baptist Home for the Aged; F. T. Gates report; Turkey missionary; Presbyterian Church; timberlands in Kentucky; Mayyou Mission (poor children's relief); job applicant; personal loan; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); lecturer; temperance work; Missionary Training School; St. Luke's Hospital; industrial education; Cleveland Homeopathic Hospital; Yorkville Dispensary and Hospital for Women and Children; Heidelberg Compound Oxygen Company; business loan; Baptist Ministers' Aid Society; Baptist Ministers' Home, Fenton, Michigan.
    - Northrup - Nott, 191 Pages (Box 29, Folder 227, Reel 26, Folder 0001)
      Chicago Baptist Theological Seminary; John D. Rockefeller contributions; personal aid; University of Chicago; recommendation of pastors for Euclid Avenue Baptist Church; personal matters; Methodist Church; Baptist Church; school teacher and principal; education of John D. Rockefeller's daughters.
    - [Noyes] Nutt - Nye, 133 Pages (Reel 26, Frame 0192, Box 29, Folder 228)
      Euclid Avenue Baptist Church Sunday school and mission work; personal aid; paintings for sale; Loring School; West Africa missionary; Baptist Church.
    - Oakes - Olcott, 147 Pages (Reel 26, Frame 0325, Box 30, Folder 229)
      Ice dealers; Baptist Church; personal aid; Ireland missionary; New York Sabbath Committee; Committee of One Hundred; St. Luke's Hospital; tax refund; personal loan; Methodist Episcopal Church; Richmond & West Point Terminal Railway & Warehouse Company; business loan; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) International Committee; College Students' Conference; author seeks aid for book; Standard Oil Company executive committee; National Transit Company; Union Oil Company; financial matters; Standard Oil Trust shares; telegraph lines; real estate; pipelines; personal matters; John D. Rockefeller's schoolteacher; Saratoga Stables; job applicant; ship launching; paintings for sale; Jerry McAuley Cremorne Mission; Germany missionary; German Baptist Publication House; gas and electric fixtures; Central Park horse speeding driveway; Road Horse Association.
    - Olden - Olson, 97 Pages (Reel 26, Frame 0472, Box 30, Folder 230)
      Colored Baptist Church; landscape architects at Forest Hill and Pocantico Hills; Cleveland Choral Union; Cleveland Vocal Society; Old Ladies Home in New York; John D. Rockefeller employee (porter); Methodist Episcopal Church and its mission work among Swedish immigrants.
    - Oncken - Osborn, E. N., 197 Pages (Reel 26, Frame Frame 0569, Box 30, Folder 231)
      Student assistance; musical education; Germany missionary; street sprinkling; character reference; North Western Orphan Asylum; Oregon Pacific Railroad Company; Ireland schools; trotting horses; business loan; Embossing Oil Company; job applicant; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church Sunday school; search for new pastor; livery stables; personal aid; "Cleveland Press."
    - Osborn, L. - Oxnard, 132 Pages (Reel 26, Frame 0766, Box 30, Folder 232)
      Personal aid; personal loan; Baptist Church; telephone line connections; Rochester Theological Seminary, president; John D. Rockefeller contributions to seminary and Baptist Churchs; Vacuum Oil Works; defense of John D. Rockefeller; American Baptist Education Society; Cleveland Grays; liquor for sale; dealer in soaps and cremes; Free Home Hospital Fair; Otis Brothers & Company; Colored Baptist Sunday school; German Baptist Church; outdoors magazine; business proposal; Denison University; National Archaeological Association; investment advice; Standard Oil Company fuel oil department; painting for sale.
    - Paalzaer - Paine, Sidney B., 134 Pages (Box 30, Folder 233, Reel 26, Frame 0898)
      Gas service at 4 West 54th Street; Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences; Spelman Seminary, president; Atlanta Baptist Female Seminary; personal aid; job applicant; sheriff's jury; Union League Club; Baptist Church; Baptist Freedmen's Mission; American Baptist Home Mission Society; "Forum" articles on business outlook in 1893; Mendelsohn Glee Club; Rochester Theological Seminary library; Central Kansas College; plumber; Grand Army of the Republic.
    - Paine, Silas H. - Parmele, 116 Pages (Box 30, Folder 234, Reel 27, Frame 0001)
      Baptist mission work; Standard Oil Company executive; lubricating oil; refined oil committee; personal aid; personal loans; Deutsche Poliklinik (German clinic in New York); American Museum of Natural History; Actors Fund of America; Adelbert College; public libraries; job applicant; student assistance; public school teacher; Baptist Church; temperance work; Society of Friends; Grand Army Mission; proposed Pan-Republican Congress; publishers; Philadelphia Gas Improvement Company; books for sale; lumber dealer; personal friend; real estate; Salvation Army; Society for the Prevention of Crime; Gospel Temperance Mission; Humane Society; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church Sunday school.
    - Parmely - Payton, 188 Pages (Box 31, Folder 235, Reel 27, Frame 0117)
      Real estate; property management; mortgages; personal aid; American Baptist Home Mission Society; tailors; Sunday observance; Women and Children's Free Dispensary; John D. Rockefeller contributions; Baptist Church; Methodist Episcopal Church; personal loan; Young Ladies' Bible College; Binghampton Ladies' College; Baptist missionary work; temperance work; woman suffrage work; National Woman Suffrage Association; Cleveland Tabernacle Music Hall; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); German Baptist Church; business loan; Episcopal Church; oil coins for sale; interior decorators; supervision of construction; French Protestant College; Standard Oil Company, treasurer; Cleveland Rolling Mill Company; competition; negotiations; Consolidated Tank Line Company; Cincinnati flood relief; Standard Oil Trust shares; National Transit Company bonds; trotting horses; student assistance; music education.
    - Peabody - Perkins, D. W., 190 Pages (Box 31, Folder 236, Reel 27, Frame 0305)
      Religious publications; Baptist Social Union; personal aid; personal loan; Standard Oil Trust shares; Wisconsin Central Railroad Company; Baptist Church; Vassar College; music education; Baptist missionary work; real estate; safe deposit boxes; student assistance; Yale Divinity School; Opera Comique; business proposal; Cleveland Diet Dispensary and Woman's Exchange; City Hospital Children's Cottage; job applicant; Women's Baptist Home Mission Society; Colored Baptist Church; Africa missionary; Texas Negro Mission School; University of Rochester; F. T. Gates report; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); Sanitary Aid Society; books for sale; Trinity School; Humane Society; horses; mineral collection; University of Chicago; People's Mission; Equitable Life Assurance Society.
    - Perkins, Joseph - Pfeiffer, 134 Pages (Box 31, Folder 237, Reel 27, Frame 0495)
      Attorneys; Lake View Cemetery Association; Central Friendly Inn; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); temperance work; Garfield Monument Fund; real estate; Baptist Church; WCTU factionalism and internal politics; political matters; Colored Baptist Church School in Texas; student assistance; Rochester Theological Seminary; Parcel Carrier Company; iron and steel industry; Knoxville College; Denison University (John D. Rockefeller resignation from board); Cook Academy; Farmers and Merchants Oil & Guano Company; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); job applicant; Missouri, Kansas & Texas Railway Company.
    - Phelps - Phipps, 171 Pages (Box 31, Folder 238, Reel 27, Frame 0629)
      John D. Rockefeller cousin; Baptist Church; real estate; Philharmonic Club; personal aid; student assistance; business loan; Homeopathic Hospital College; Maternity Home; Baptist Social Union; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); John D. Rockefeller contributions to temperance work; political matters; Women's Christian Temperance Union factionalism and internal politics; stained glass.
    - Picaya - Plummer, 128 Pages (Box 31, Folder 239)
      Baptist Young People's Union; Methodist Church; Baptist Church; personal aid; investment advice; job applicant; business proposal; Standard Oil Company employee; real estate; Kalamazoo College; Valparaiso University; tapestries for sale; Racine College; orchids; Bohemian Mission; student assistance; Ceylon missionary; Presbyterian Church; interview request; Woman's Christian Association; separation of church and state; American Fine Arts Society; Colby, Abbot & Hoyt; personal matters.
    - Pogson - Porter, G. (Mrs.), 162 Pages (Box 31, Folder 240, Reel 28, Frame 0001)
      Baptist Church; Spelman Seminary; Women's Baptist Home Mission Society; job applicant; personal aid; John D. Rockefeller schoolmate; Home School for Young Ladies and Children; Cleveland Homeopathic Hospital; business proposal; Ohio Sabbath-School Union; American Sunday School Union; F. T. Gates report; American Temperance Union; Colored Baptist Church; Symphony Society; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); Central Friendly Inn; American Baptist Home Mission Society, Church Edifice Department; Mexico missionary; John D. Rockefeller contributions to church buildings; WCTU factionalism and internal politics.